<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.5.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://darrenhaken.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://darrenhaken.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-09-06T11:29:20+01:00</updated><id>https://darrenhaken.github.io/</id><title type="html">Darren Haken</title><subtitle>Musings about software development and technical leadership. Interested in devops, cloud, big data.
</subtitle><author><name>Darren Haken</name><email>darrenhaken@gmail.com</email><uri>https://www.darrenhaken.com</uri></author><entry><title type="html">Kaizen 101 - From Scrum to Kanban</title><link href="https://darrenhaken.github.io/2015/01/19/kaizen-in-the-trenches.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Kaizen 101 - From Scrum to Kanban" /><published>2015-01-19T22:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2015-01-19T22:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://darrenhaken.github.io/2015/01/19/kaizen-in-the-trenches</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://darrenhaken.github.io/2015/01/19/kaizen-in-the-trenches.html">&lt;p&gt;Over the last few years I’ve worked with many teams and fully embraced the agile mindset.
It’s been a roller coaster of a journey but I have to say I’ve loved every minute of it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most teams generally start by adopting Scrum as their new project management process.
This means delivering in iterations, cadences such as daily stand ups and retrospectives but most importantly higher collaboration across the team.
However, I often start to get a niggling voice in the back of my mind once the team starts to stabilise with their process.
I often feel we’ve moved to a ‘water-scrum-fall’ methodology whereby we’re simply delivering in smaller chunks but without everything else the agile manifesto promised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We should be asking questions like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Are we even delivering the right thing?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;By delivering smaller chunks of software are we delivering value sooner?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What’s slowing us down and blocking us?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started to think that Scrum may be foundation towards what the agile manifesto originally set out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;enter-kaizen&quot;&gt;Enter Kaizen&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A superstar team needs to be disruptive, continually evolving and acting quickly to identify waste.
But how does a team begin to make this part of their DNA?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A business philosophy formed in Japan by Toyota, Kaizen means &lt;em&gt;“continuous improvement”&lt;/em&gt;.
This ideology really resonates with me. I firmly believe if we aren’t trying to improve ourselves then we risk becoming complacent and inevitably slowing down our progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s important to realise this is a full team effort! In Toyota participation is close to 100%
with each employee expected to offer at least one suggestion per year for improvement.
Without experimenting and taking risks to improve, we may miss potential opportunities for greatness.
Even if things don’t quite work out as we planned, failure is still an opportunity to learn for our next experiment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve seen teams embrace Kaizen in many ways including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reducing the number of defects&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Faster delivery&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increased customer satisfaction&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Faster recovery from disasters&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Elimination of waste which impedes delivery&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;starting-your-kaizen-journey&quot;&gt;Starting your Kaizen journey&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try and &lt;em&gt;visualise your process&lt;/em&gt; and strive for a &lt;em&gt;sustainable pace&lt;/em&gt; at delivering software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On projects I’ve worked on we use a physical board to visualise our process, which starts from customer requests and ends when they’re released into the wild.
We refer to this as our value stream. It’s important we visualise our value stream as humans tend to be really good at processing information when using visual aids.
We are also incredibly skilled at forgetting things; visual cues are great reminders and an easy way to digest information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is an example of a project board:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/kanban-wall.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Project board&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By visualising your value stream you can:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Quickly see all the work in progress&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Spot impediments/blockers preventing a feature from being delivered&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improve communication between team members&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Begin to make changes and visually see how it impacts your project&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last point is key as I want as many opportunities as I can to see how changes affect the project (both good and bad).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-the-sustainable-pace-shouldnt-i-be-working-at-my-full-capacity&quot;&gt;Why the sustainable pace, shouldn’t I be working at my full capacity?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve often seen teams become obsessed with 100% utilisation which can sometimes be a side effect of focusing on velocity as the only means of measuring the teams success.
However this comes at a price, flexibility. If the team is maxed out they can’t quickly respond to change as they already have too much to handle!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alternatively we could control the amount of work flowing through the value stream to match the teams capacity.
Kanban is a great system to do this and often refers to this as &lt;em&gt;limiting your work in progress (WIP)&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project board above shows WIP limits for each column of our value stream which is indicated by red bars marked below.
For example there is a limit of 2 features that can be implemented concurrently in development, which matches to the two developer pairs on the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Controlling WIP allows the opportunity to reduce the demand (only slightly) and introduce slack to incorporate experiments into the team.
For example what if the developers could have an afternoon per week where they reached out for feedback from our users?
We can then incorporate what we learn into future development and potentially increase our user base.
It might sound crazy but experiments like this are often breakthroughs for the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;measuring-is-key&quot;&gt;Measuring is key&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To understand the impact our changes have on the project it’s important to measure our progress and understand our successes and failures.
Remember, failures are another opportunity to learn for our next experiment!
Before starting your Kaizen journey, gather measurements of your project to act as your baseline.
We need a baseline to understand what impact we’ve had and validate whether the hypothesis was correct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In future posts I’ll discuss some of the Kaizen moments I’ve witnessed on projects and the techniques used to measure.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Darren Haken</name><email>darrenhaken@gmail.com</email><uri>https://www.darrenhaken.com</uri></author><category term="agile" /><category term="lean" /><summary type="html">Over the last few years I’ve worked with many teams and fully embraced the agile mindset. It’s been a roller coaster of a journey but I have to say I’ve loved every minute of it!</summary></entry></feed>